<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on anti-ism-ism</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on anti-ism-ism</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Testing assumptions of the data-generating process underlying Experience Sampling</title>
      <link>/post/2017-05-19-testing-assumptions-of-the-data-generating-process-underlying-experience-sampling/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 09:50:02 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-05-19-testing-assumptions-of-the-data-generating-process-underlying-experience-sampling/</guid>
      <description>Anomalous diffusion: Individual particle tracking vs. Ensemble averages Particles are individuals too! A timeseries of daily mood: down Test for level and trend stationarity Test for AR, ARCH or an optimal ARIMA process Structural decomposition Conclusions NEXT: Dynamics in state space Anomalous diffusion: Individual particle tracking vs. Ensemble averages A recent article by Bos et al. (2017)1 in which the authors compared network measures derived from cross-sectional (between-individual) and within-individual</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reproduce $e$ to $18,457,734,525,360,901,453,873,570$ decimal places!</title>
      <link>/post/2017-05-09-pandigital-numbers-and-functions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2017 09:50:02 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-05-09-pandigital-numbers-and-functions/</guid>
      <description>Why? No reason, this is the accidental mathematician category. Pandigital numbers Pandigital numbers aren’t that special, it’s a number that has all digits from 1-9, or, 0-9 in it. For example: 381654729 is a pandigital number (with some extra properties) Pandigital functions As Complexity Scientists (and musicians and artists in general) know: Interesting things will happen when the degrees of freedom available</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oh right... I used to blog</title>
      <link>/post/2017-03-02-oh-right-i-used-to-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2017 16:35:02 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-03-02-oh-right-i-used-to-blog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A beginning is the time for taking the most delicate care that the balances are correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; Fom Manual of Muad’Dib by Prinses Irulan (Herbert, 1965)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been a while&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you still have a while&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R Effect Size CI tutorial</title>
      <link>/post/2015-05-05-osc-r-esci-tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-05-05-osc-r-esci-tutorial/</guid>
      <description>Using R to Compute Effect Size Confidence Intervals This is a demonstration of using R in the context of hypothesis testing by means of Effect Size Confidence Intervals. In other words, we’ll calculate confidence intervals based on the distribution of a test statistic under the assumption that \(H_0\) is false, the noncentral distribution of a test statistic.
Discrete distributions: Count data and proportions  Discrete CI ≠ Approximately Continuous CI Noncentral CIs around the Odds Ratio of Fisher’s Exact Test Example: Time, Money, and Morality  Continuous distributions: Standardised sample means  Standardised, but on which measure of dispersion?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time = Money: The Morality of Being Accurate.</title>
      <link>/post/2015-03-07-time-money-morality/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-03-07-time-money-morality/</guid>
      <description>A Post-Publication Peer-Review (3PR) of: Time, Money, and Morality by Gino, F., &amp;amp; Mogilner, C. (online, 2013). Time, Money, and Morality. Psychological Science. DOI: 10.1177/0956797613506438
 Introduction The Time, Money, and Morality article has been HIBAR-ed on Twitter and the Blogosphere (e.g., by Rolf Zwaan and Greg Francis ) and the discussion seems to revolve around the validity of the inferences based p-values close to 0.05 (e.g., they raise suspicions of p-hacking).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>